[Music]
this is software engineering radio the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at se-radio.net
sc radio is brought to you by the ieee
computer society by ieee software
magazine
online at computer.org software
become an autonomous digital enterprise
and your business can achieve a game
status
intelligent predictive systems
effortless automation
and technology and people working in
harmony
this is the autonomous digital
enterprise
visit bmc.com a game for more
information
welcome to software engineering radio
i'm akshay munchale
and today i'll be talking to doug gral
doug is a technical marketing manager at
redis labs
he's a passionate developer and open
source advocate with a deep background
across the open source community
prior to redis labs he held positions at
the likes of red hat
map r mongodb couch base and oracle
we covered redis previously in episode
209 this episode will go over the basics
and then we'll talk about more emerging
use cases and how it's currently being
used and managed
doug welcome to the show hello welcome
very happy to be here so
thanks for introduction great so let's
start off on a very high level
can you talk about what redis is and
what it's used for
so redis is one of the many database
that you have on the market
and it's part of this nosql movement
that
was created in 2001 2007 i will say
where
you you need new database to under new
use cases
around speed scalability flexibility
and redis was created as an open source
project by salvatore
when he needed a very very fast
dictionary for
data you want to access and he created
in open source a key value store
purely in memory it's the initial dna of
this database and over time in more than
10 years now
the community added more and more
features to the database
so what sort of applications is redis
used and in
so technically it's using almost
any type of application but it's solving
one of the problem very quickly and it's
very fast access to the data so this is
why you will see
as a entry point for the projects use
that use release
radius is used as a cache it's used as a
session store
as initial project and this is one of
the reasons it was built because
when you build an application you want
to access the data as fast as possible
and especially if you know that you will
access the data multiple time in a row
like a sessions or user sessions
it doesn't make sense to have to go back
to disk or do a long
network call to do another database and
so on
so people start to use release as a
simple key value store in memory for
this type of use case
on overtime because it's very simple to
use
they start to do more and more things
with the data
and keeping the same logic of being very
very simple to use
the community and radius has 10
different
core data structures from single strings
from list from set from
hashes to type of data structures that
will help you to solve specific problems
for your application that go a lot
beyond a simple session toward cash you
can
you can use that to you to store your
e-commerce kind of
cart with information about what you
want to buy to do some recommendations
in very very fast access so if you look
at it from a use case point of view
because it's used to share data between
different calls
or different services it could be used
in retail or e-commerce to
build a cache at the top of a catalog to
build a session of a user
cache over a catalog session of users
it's
almost any business you do today if you
talk about
shared configurations because you want
to have different services in different
technology
that want to share for example a
specific configuration
you can use redis you can have a service
in php that will
save some data a service in another
language
that will want to access this data and
this could be just to action some event
or exchange some configurations
so this is why uh in term of use case on
industry
i like to say release is everywhere
usually when you meet a developer into a
when you work on a radius and you go to
a developer conference or you do a
meetup or something
you go in the room and you say who is
using reddis or who has been touching
reddis
you are sure that almost everybody has
seen heard about it or they know that
somewhere
it's there because it's also really
embedded in many many solutions you know
like cms like
e-commerce platform it's used internally
by default
to cache the data so this is a kind of
the dna
speed on simplicity and scalability for
your data
so a lot of the speed and access it's
accelerated by keeping
things resident in memory as opposed to
disk in databases is that right
yes you see this is a choice that is
already steam and
the philosophy of freddies has been is
to we want that to be in memory
like that you have have consistent kind
of latency
so usually as we look at when we monitor
an application we will look
around one or less milliseconds to get
the operation done
but the good part of being in memory it
will always
be that it's you just need to be careful
about how you scale
in the sense that we don't necessarily
store the data in memory only
that means you can choose when you
configure your radius to say
i want the data also stored on disk
just in case you have to stop the
already so if you crash one node when
you restart you will load the data from
disk to memory
but when you work in your application it
always go
into the memory and all the data set is
in memory
so and the main reason it's to be sure
that me as a developer i have tested my
applications i know that these specific
operations is taking
half of me off milliseconds or one
milliseconds to get the data
and to do the comparison between these
two lists if i do that today
if i do that tomorrow only if i do that
in one week you will keep with the same
kind of performance because the data
will always be in memory on traditional
database
you may have the data that you have not
used so let's say you want to compare
two lists
and it's right now in memory great but
over time
because it will not be used you will go
back to disk
and one your application will need it
you will have to go go from this to
memory and then
get back to the user so this is one of
the things that make
redis very very interesting for
application when you need to under
what we call the real time in the sun
that you know that you
that's time you will spend to get access
to to retrieve the data out of the
database
so what sort of data do you normally
store in redis i know there are certain
data structures that it supports out of
the box can you walk us through some of
the simple ones that are commonly used
so you have so you have 10 data type
inside release code what we call already
score is really is already you are
thinking about when you're asking me the
questions the reason why i say ready
score is because
and we will talk about that over time is
we are
releasing as a as an extension mechanism
that is called modules that allow you to
create
new data structure on your command so in
redis core
you have you have the key and when you
have the key then you will
associate a value to it this is why we
we talk about a key value store but
people will often say oh key value store
it's a simple key on its simple value
in radius it's not the case it's a key
simple key
very easy to define you define the way
you want
the smaller the better why because it's
kept in memory but
it has to be long enough or clear enough
to as a user that you understand what
this key is it is a uuid that has no
clue
how what it means it's not necessarily
easy to read
so associated to this key you will have
a string
that could be up to a 500 megabyte
be careful okay because it's you don't
want to always
because it's not only the place that you
put that in memory it's a network that
you have to pay so
you have a string it's very the string
is very often used to
if you have to cache an information
about a subset of html content
an information about a user informations
result of a web services call and you
don't really care about how it's
structured you will use a string
you also have hashes so behind your key
you will have a set of other field
name on value so typically instead of
having a long string
that contains uh using an xml or json
uh for some information about a profile
user like your first name last name and
so on
with a hash you will be able to in
behind the key i have the name
the field name name first name last name
and so on
the benefits of that is the fact that
you can have as many field as you want
so you could be thousands of thousands
of fields
on when you save when you when you
retrieve when you do an increment you
can have a subset
of this field so the hash is a way of
organizing a way of structured contact
or street
data structure so typically if you do a
product catalog you may use this
as a data structure where you will have
the is a skew as a key
and then a set of fields and when you
retrieve and
communicate with the database you will
only save
or retrieve a subset of this field
depending of your business api
that you want to deal with so in
addition to this core
very used very used data structure you
also have
sorted set on set so this is a you can
put value
in a set and you can query them on add
on
manipulate or navigate into this on
sorted set it's the same you have value
associated to a key with
a score on a common use case for the
started set
is ranking in gaming so if you want to
have the top five player for
specific things or what are the most
downloaded
features and so on so you want to
organize content in a way you can sort
on query very efficiently
on this on a specific sort order by
you will just associate the key that
will be top
top 10 user for this game and you will
have the name of the user
a score and so on and when you query
that you will just have the
capabilities of reading this
and you also have lists so lists are
very basic structure
basically not necessarily basic in the
way they are implemented but the way you
manipulate
and with everything you can do is pop
an ad feature at the top at the
beginning or the end
of the list so this is uh many of the
core features that use for
for applications and then you have other
like pub sub
features that allow the user to do
publish of subscribe data on event
it's used for notifications it's used
for
communicating between two different
services in real time like that you have
one system calling another one
and in release 5 one of the
data structures that i really really
like because i work a lot with messaging
technology before it's ready streams
it's a log of events like a kafka
more or less like a kafka so you can
send an event store the event to the
database and then you have a set of
consumers that can read a part of it
read entirely or retry so allowing you
to do some good on
advanced messaging applications using
release
out of the box so is that like um a
durable
messaging system like kafka or is there
a difference there
no it is durable it's it's uh with the
trade-off
of being in memory right it's always
it's so
when i say being in memory once again it
does not only sit
in memory it could be save on disk you
choose when do you want to save
when you configure on when you start
your radius instance you can say
i want only memory so i don't want to
store anything on disk
or i want to save on disk every
six hour every four hours so this could
be good if you for example have a big
cache and you want to
you know you are exporting every day a
big data set from the mainframe into
radius to have a very fast access and
you don't want to have all the
processing
even if some something crashed in one of
your container and so on
but you can also do happen only
so happen only will be every transaction
or every mutation
or every second you can save data on
disk so when you
if we talk about this specific use case
of
having a persisted log when you do a add
x add is a command x add is a command x
add one message
x x add another message you can choose
to save on disk
every time so it will not have a bit
impact on performance because it's done
asynchronously
so we say it's a single thread
we often talk about the single threaded
application in redis it's true on the
server side from operations but
everything that is related to
replication that is related to saving on
disk
it's in a different thread to do to
avoid impacting the performance so in
this case you will save the data on disk
so it's persisted and you it allows you
to play again with
the data whatever you want i just want
to add something a little bit specific
on this
is as you know as you mentioned i'm
working for redis labs and redis labs is
adding also some other features to the
community versions
in the enterprise version on one of the
use cases
it's you can use something called
radisson flash that is only available in
enterprise but
the idea is to if you have a bigger data
set with cold
or cooler data on hot data you can have
some of the data that will not sit in
memory all the time
keys will stay in memory some of the
value will be on disk
and in this case we are closer to a very
very very fast
database that is disk in memory
so in some sense redis is used as a
cache on top of other data stores so you
can have updates going into your primary
data store
up through redis maybe it's going out of
redis how do you manage recency of data
so you have many different ways of doing
that
and also i will you know just to be a
little bit
controversial is you also have a lot of
people that using now redis
as their primary database for their
application
you can use and you should use redis as
your database
if the data model fits if it's if you
don't need it present somewhere else
it's possible
so to go back to your questions about
yes when it's used as a cache
the biggest challenge with all the
cached
caching technologies on caching
infrastructure on architecture is when
do you invalidate
how do you know that you have to go back
to the initial data
data so here you have different
options depending on this is you have no
magic here it's really first the
developer has to understand
the data is manipulating so for example
if i
if i take a very basic example that is
very simple to implement
and in this case it's quite easy suppose
you are calling a web service that is
giving you the the weather forecast
in your in your kind of area you are
building a
a farm agriculture kind of applications
and you want to give
forecast forecast will not change every
five minutes right it's
it's okay if you cache for one hour or
two hours of forecast for the next five
days
so in this case in release the simple
way
simplest simplest way will be to simply
say
put a ttl a time to leave and
expirations of
one hour like that as a developer you
have nothing to do you set the value
so you call the web service for the
weather you set the value in radius and
you say in one hour
delete it it will be done for you when
you have some
something that is more complex it will
really depends do you have access can
you have some notifications about
the initial data source and what we see
more and more
is we were talking about ready streams
on kafka
or at least two minutes ago
so if you are using an event sourcing
kind of approach or messaging approach
you will use that to invalidate your
cache you can receive the event and say
when i receive this type of event i will
invalidate the cache
and you have two ways of doing that
either you really invalidate the cache
you just delete the object
or you can also ask the system to go
into the main data source
and put that in the cache this is also
how we see a lot of cdc
change data capture integration so in
this case you plug your
initial database that captures the
transactions and you push
the event inside alice so to
make to keep the data up to date based
on the initial
data source so in this case it's coming
from the
the golden record that is your mainframe
or your oracle database on mysql
pushing data back to uh to release
lately we
um using a modules called radius gears
so it's a part of the ecosystem that is
available in open source you have an
interesting
use for that it's it's doing
a cache right through release in this
case your application can
interact only with redis but when you
modify something in redis you will
push update in your relational database
in this case you if you modify something
in redux it's always up to date
and you will eventually using ready
streams and so on push
update into your relational database so
you see you have you have different ways
of doing that
the key in this part is when you work as
a developer as an architect it's try to
first understand that caching you always
have these questions about
how long my data will be valid what's
the event that makes this data invalid
is it something that i can control is it
something that is only time based
and if it's some things i i can control
what will be the best
solution for that so you mentioned
this time to live for certain data
structures right so let's say
something actually expires and then an
application is trying to look for
that particular key does it actually
reach out to the database first and then
do a put on redis or is it just reaching
out to redis and then redis
if there's a cache miss populates it
from the data store
um how does that work it's intel i like
the way you ask the questions because it
makes me thinking
it goes back to the initial dna of redis
as simple as possible make it simple
what does that mean
that means it doesn't do anything for
you besides
expiration so what i found is i put if
we go back to this
example where i have to call the
database or a web service
after one hour if you try to get it
and you will you will not return the
value you will say it's nil or
the key does not exist what happened in
this case it's depending on exactly when
is it in the process the key will be
really
out of the database because you have
some cleanup jobs and that will really
delete
or what's happening if you if you arrive
just
one second after one millisecond after
the expiration you could
you will check if the time to leave has
been done and if it's done it will
delete and return new
so by default you will not try to go
back to
call the web service we call the
database for that
this is usually something that you put
inside your application
and you have many systems that does that
out of the box but it's not inside
radius you know when you work for
example with uh
with spring uh in java you have many
frameworks you can have
you can activate some kind of level to
cache
in this case in this case what will
happen is hibernate
spring data and so on will work
automatically by themselves
to see if they need to put the data in
release or not
and they will deal with accessing the
database what you can do
you can build some stuff yourself to say
when uh
when i inside the database using some
lua script using some
specific services or even a module you
can build to call the database yourself
but the thing we have to be aware on
and careful is we want hedis to be
as fast as simple as efficient as
possible so
where is the best way to call the data
so to get the the
data out of the golden record or the
system the main system of record it's
really based on your application on how
fast
it has to go the traditional way is
i try in the cache if it's not in the
cache i call
the database i store in release and i
return the value like that after
it's back into into release that's
interesting
one of the other things that i know
about tradis is
redis is also known for probabilistic
data structures and it's a topic we
covered previously in episode 358.
can you tell us what probabilistic data
structures are present in redis and how
they are commonly used
so so you have in the main in the core
you have ibr paralog log that allows you
to
increment value in an efficient way so
the idea is to
count value billions of billion of
values
keeping the number very very very small
so the memory size is very very small
if you want to come the number of hits
on a specific
movie or something for example you are
youtube and you want to have a quick
calculation so one of the thing will be
to
see how many times a specific resource
is available and has been accessed
so the the reaper log log will do that
and it will
optimize the size and it will stay to
12k in memory very efficient
even if you have big number so price to
pay in this case it's an approximation
of the data so if you want to know
exactly
to the exactly exact unit it won't be
this case
another this one is in core in in
radisco
when you use one of the modules
developed by the community it's called
bloom filter or radius bloom and this
wise is
based on bloom filter so it's to check
in a very very very efficient way
if something is in the list or not
and and the interesting part is
i just have to be right in the in in
the way i express that is it's if you
want to
quickly know if a value that you are
checking
is part of a list or not and instead of
having to control
a very large set of data you will do a
guess
the guess that will be more or less uh
[Music]
the fault or the tolerance will be
bigger and smaller depending on how you
configure and how want you want to be
your space in memory
so the idea is if it says
yes it is in this now i have it
i have a dope but the idea is if it will
you will
do a check is this value part of my uh
my filter yes if it's part of my filter
you are sure that is in the filter
if it's no if it's no
now i have a top but maybe that
yeah yeah yeah one in one case it's
maybe it is or maybe
and i should under on one use case for
that i was discussing with a developer
you know um right now it's aws reinvent
so you have a lot of conferences on why
and right now happening and i was
discussing with one of the users of
freddy's in india and they are doing
eco payment platform so they have many
many
merchants and when they want to do a b
testing a b testing
between different features they will
have to they have millions of customers
and they want to check if this customer
is part of this city
and if he has a specified a specific
item in the last six months or
last 24 hours i want to show this
feature and i do not oh i do not want to
show this feature because i'm testing
new fit
new kind of picture this has to be this
decision
has to be very very fast the rules is
very simple
is it part of this list this list or
this list
but doing this two or three tests has to
be very very very efficient because you
have to do that for
millions of users with thousands of
features or hundreds of features so this
is typically where
initially in redis they were using
sets and they were comparing sets
but the issue it was taking a little bit
too much time even in release
so they switch to prom filter allowing
to have instead of
a few thousand of merchants to have more
than one million of merchants into the
database and be very efficient so the
idea of being probabilistic is yes you
are not 100 sure
but you do it very very very fast so
you're allowing you to add new
features to your system you just have to
understand not like not like i just did
exactly what the trade-off is because
it's all about trade-offs yeah
well uh you know with this since it's
not an exact answer
uh but it's also being served from the
cache you have a risk that it might just
go away
like you know your instance restarts or
something now whatever you have in your
bloom filter is actually lost
so how do you reconstruct that um how do
these probabilistic data structures come
back
up online and uh give you an efficient
answer uh
reasonably fast so so the way
my answer for that and it's you
probably feel funny in the way make it
make sure that it doesn't disappear so
how do you do that
you can use persistence on disk it's one
case
the other one and this is if your data
if your data in radius is important and
it's complex to
build because it's either a large volume
or because it's a bloom filter so
it's long it has it's based on the
volume is small but it's based on a
million of entries you have to
you should use persistence but more
importantly you should use high
availability you should put in a radius
in a way that you have master
and replica so you have a copy of your
data
inside the cluster inside your
environment so it's very easy to do with
release
so you just create a cluster
or an environment where you have
multiple radius running in multiple
machines
so every time you will modify your value
it will be replicated to another
node so like that if something happen it
will
fail over to this node so i don't answer
your questions because i don't have an
answer if you have if it's millions of
million of million
you have to save the data somewhere but
you don't do it manually
you use persistence and you use
replication giving high availability to
your radius
instances okay yeah that makes sense
i want to talk a little bit about the
query aspect of it
so you know you can do look up by keys
you can look for existence
checks on lists uh but what is the
concurrency model for all of this is it
always like consistent with respect to
another write operation coming in
um how does that work in in redis is it
transactional
so every operation is atomic nothing
will happen in uh
in only one operation after the other so
the part is
you can guess and you understand what's
happening so
you don't have transaction in the sense
you can't you cannot do
begin transactions modify modify modify
and roll back
but what you can do using pipeline
and transaction is you can be sure that
operation one two three four are
happening
one after the other and nobody else will
come because being single threaded that
doesn't mean that
you cannot have multiple clients running
on this on the same server obviously you
have many clients
but with the api that you have inside
release
you can be sure and you can force when
you need to
to do exactly what you mean for example
you want to
increment a value set something in
another key
retrieve some values and you want to be
sure that nothing happened between
these first operations and this third
operation only these three operations
have to go
have to go together so this is what we
call a transaction in relis
you can do that this is called
transaction on pipelining obviously you
should not do that all the time because
it will impact the other clients that
will wait a little bit until this three
operation has been done to continue
so in this case it's managed by by
release
server itself okay interesting
become an autonomous digital enterprise
and your business can achieve
a game status intelligent predictive
systems
effortless automation and technology and
people working in harmony
this is the autonomous digital
enterprise
visit bmc.com a game for more
information
i want to switch gears a little bit and
talk about some more emerging use cases
that are coming up with redis
i see that it's being used in machine
learning stacks i see it's being used in
search
graph databases so there's there's this
whole
array of new use cases that this is
being used in uh can you talk about some
of the more interesting ones that you
think
are non-traditional uses of redis that
is being used today
and some examples so one of well you
know
it's it's a very good sequel to what you
just asked in terms of you know
transaction or querying
is one of the things release is very
fast redis is quite easy to use the api
is quite simple for the developers
one of the challenges is suppose we have
and i will go to the to
the exact answer you are the exact
question you ask is
i use hashes to store all my
connected users and last week connected
users so i have
hundreds of thousands of entries but i
would like to do a simple query say can
you give me
the number or the top five or the number
of
connected user current connected user
coming from
from california if i want to do that
with redis core without anything i will
have to manage myself because i cannot
do a full scan
so what i will have to do is i will have
to use a hash to store the user profile
that contains the state but i have to
somewhere have a list
of the states of the connected users to
be able to get this value so i will
manage my index on the relation between
my hash
on my list of connected user for a
specific state
so it's it's a use case that people use
but only very advanced developers
will be able to do that the people that
have the time to design this and really
really really need
this kind of milliseconds
latency in reality this request
it was becoming more on more regular
in the discussion of i want to do that
so this is exactly why
redis community and redis lab started to
develop modules
that answer this type of question so one
of the
first modules was how we can do indexing
querying on full text search on inside
release
to take exactly the examples that i
showed is you want to store the hashes
and you want to be able without having
to manage yourself just creating an
index saying okay
i have a hash that has a key the the
pattern of the key it's
user column something everything that
starts with user i want to index them
with
first name last name on state like that
i will be able to do some queries
so one of the use cases that is coming
more and more often is to be able to
query by value
in a very simple way and it's done using
a ready search module
so in this case it's just by providing
more advanced capabilities in querying
and aggregation so you don't need to go
to a third party tool to do that
using the same approach it's developers
want to create
complex applications using graph data
graph database they want to be able to
be quickly
do anomalies or comparison
to find some pattern and be able to
analyze an impact of something
and the goal of the community of release
on the on the modules was to give a
module that will help them to do that so
this is why
this graph was built so you see querying
on indexing
doing graph queries and for the same
reason you have time
series so be able to organize in a very
simple way
using the simplicity of redis where you
can organize time series do queries by
tag
find a very fast interval and so on into
into the data and for this
the the way we approach that as a
community and as a company
is to what are the main use cases in
terms
of i want to work with this set of data
and provide
a data structure and the commands so
typically
you will see we talk about bloom filter
search for indexing and querying data by
value
including full text search time series
graph database and you also have gears i
talk about it's kind of some eventing
system or serverless programming because
you can add some programmation or
application inside your database and you
talk about ai
so artificial intelligence machine
learning globally
is becoming more and more important in
many
enterprise and what's happening
more data more need you need
a fast uh you need a fast access to the
data
this is where radius comes to the
picture and what happens is
people can store the data as a cache
like you we talk at the beginning of the
discussion but what is more interesting
can i cache
a part of my model can i use the
transfers and from tensorflow or
something inside release
so the community and redis labs has
built
radius ai to allow you to add inside
radius
a part of your artificial intelligence
kind of infrastructure and architecture
to make
your application faster and easy to
manage so is it fair to say that it kind
of like caches the model for you to give
you the response based on whatever
approximation that the machine learning
model does rather than it's
rather than being used for learning
itself yes exactly
it's more towards the result to the the
result of the model and the inference of
i've not personally spent a lot of time
on this module
we are uh we see we are adding more and
more uh
example as we speak uh it's something
that is quite important right these days
you have a lot of investment in the
in the development to show more example
but the idea
it's more on the execution of the model
in the application to be as fast as
possible
so you also mentioned several times
about redis gears
and it's used in serverless programming
and as a computing thing
on data can you can you walk us through
the examples in a little more detail
about what redis gears is
so so one of the one of the
questions or use case is you use release
and you want to react on some specific
event and you want to process some data
on a specific event so
for example you want obviously first of
all when i talk about
serverless or computing inside the
database
it's related to the data right it's not
to execute a web server
it's really to process and manipulate
the data that you have inside redis
do something with the data that you have
in some ways for example you want to be
able
when you have a specific event or on a
specific con
job that you want to run instead of
having to run something
outside redis you can do that inside
release
and so one example will be when you have
a specific
data or an update on a specific data you
want to
modify some other data in your overall
database so you kind of want to do a
trigger that will add some information
on modify and you want to do that as
close as possible from
inside the db instead of calling
something outside
and having the processing on all this
being outside the database to
modify again the db the idea of gears is
to be able based either on
event inside the db when you insert when
you have notified so you will have
a specific thing happening in the db
including
account so a specific scheduling then
you will execute some code
and depending on how you develop and
deploy
it could be created today in python and
we are working to implement this logic
in java on c
and so on and the idea will be and this
is important when it's at scale
because if you have a small data set
with a single process
it's you can put the process on the same
server
and you will be almost the same but
imagine you have
a distributed database so you have not
only replication
for high availability but you have
multiple process where you
what we call the clustering inside
release where you
distribute the data you shard the data
based on some keys rules
between different machines so what is
nice is
the gear itself the business logic that
is running is
on each of the machines close to the
instance
inside the instance so you will
distribute the processing in parallel so
you can imagine like a map reduce
approach of the data
because you will distribute the load you
will do some aggregations on efficient
access to the data this is what uh
what radius gears is for and uh
the idea of radius gears is two things
it's to have this
for you as a developer to use it and
expand it if you want
i use it sometime as part of the
demonstration i do is just to capture an
event
put that on a messaging system and then
you consume the event
or you have a whitebeard cache this is
uh
right behind feature where you we use
gears to
capture the event of a modification
inside redis
and some simple business logic to
connect to relational database
and do the update or delete
or create into the relational database
so in this case it's just
consuming the event manipulating the
data interacting with an external system
so um one thing i want to clarify
initially you said
that redis is single processor single
threaded gears are in line with that
single process operations or is it
outside is it asynchronously sort of
executed
so so the thing when we talk about
release as a single threaded process
it's not really on a single select
process you have other process like
saving on these replications gears
executing gears
the single process is where you interact
with the data
so when you have multiple so suppose you
have a single instance of release
and you have hundreds of client
applications writing in it
and you have many doing sets some of
doing delete some doing doing gets
and so on this command are always on the
same thread
so like like that you don't have to do
concurrency management locking on all
this stuff it's always
in the same thread this is where it's
single threaded you have other thread
outside and typically gears
is doing some threading outside so it
doesn't break the model of being single
threaded
because a single credit is when you
manipulate the data so when
when gears is writing the data it's back
to the single thread but the
execution engine is on a different
thread okay so your latency is still the
same with respect to
your operations yeah yeah or throughput
rather yeah this is really
the yeah exactly this is really the
focus of uh
of the design of redis it's to be sure
that
saving writing data reading data should
be
consistent in terms of expectation right
and the design is around that
so this is why when you size your radius
cluster you release you have kind of
some basic rules you will say
i will put one i will use
a few colors for one core for each
instance and one or more core for the
other stuff so you
you can have multiple instances of
radius on the same machine
so you will take three cores for each
instance one
additional core for gears i o and so on
and you will say i will use my 25
gigabyte of data
in each of the process and i will on an
average
obviously will change depending on the
use case of the data set but i would say
25 000 operations per seconds i can
start with that if i don't know exactly
what my use case i am safe and then you
can tune in or
a big or not so it's really optimized to
uh work on on the multiple multi-core
stuff
so you it's because it's single threaded
you know that this part of this in the
process is single threaded it's very
simple to tune
on level with the power of your machines
just keeping some
memory on core for the other part like
ios and network applications all these
kind of things
so let's say you start off using redis
to accelerate your application and then
you notice that
you need to scale up what are the signs
that tell you that you need to
sort of increase your memory footprint
or maybe even distribute and add
additional nodes
how do you how do you go about that so
one of the one of the thing is usually
you have to to to to look two things uh
to look at
is what's the latency of your
application you just to be sure you
don't overload the system
on the other part so this is the number
of operations per second in this case
you just look at
how many operations per seconds i have
on my machine
and if it starts to be to have a latency
and you look at where it's
where it's waiting is it waiting to
access the memory
and so on it's waiting to access a
specific path you will split the
database in multiple process so you will
charge the data to be sure that it
doesn't weight too much you distribute
the load in term of operations on read
and write so this one is just looking at
the latency the other part is more a
safety net
i was talking about replication for high
availability
so you can suppose you have a
one terabyte of memory inside your
machine
you can put a i've not tested it so i
don't know but you can put a
500 gigabytes of
data in one single release it will work
not an issue if you don't have millions
of operations per second
it will work perfectly but what happened
if your data we go back to the
discussion about
what happened if this crash you know you
have to do an upgrade of your server you
have to
you have a crash of the network and so
on you have replicated the data
right it's good so you have a copy it's
perfect so you will go back to the other
node it's working perfectly
but the issue with that is you still
need if this this one of the server has
totally crashed
you will need to restart the server and
you will need to recopy the 500 gigabyte
from this specific instance to a zero
other instance so it will be costly in
terms of operations on your network
so this is why one of the best practices
is to say on a single instance of radius
try to stay less than 25 gigabyte
it's not a hard limit it's just a good
practice because like that if you have
to
replicate the data restart from these
moves they do an upgrade and move the
database to another server it's a lot
faster to move 25 gigabytes
stuff than a big big thing that you have
to load back in memory so
on so to go back to your initial
questions you look at the number of
operations per second if you start to
see latency on too much weight time
between a request you have to distribute
the data
to distribute the load if your instance
are becoming too big you should
distribute the data for safety when i
say safety
something won't happen how fast it will
go back to normal
so time to recover your data is really a
really important factor there yeah
so let's say you do have a
multi-instance redis so now you have
your keys that are distributed across
different instances possibly different
clusters or
different physical machines itself
how do you find what you're looking for
is that something that's left to the
application
so no it's not so
some people will do it manually but
obviously
redis has been build to help you to
scale out
and distribute the data this is what we
call the cluster on the cluster api
so what will happen is you will
distribute the keys in small virtual
slots
of 16 000 on something
virtual slot so you have you take the
key it has a hash and it will give you a
number between
zero and 16 thousand something and this
slot
will be on one of the physical server
one of the instances so
if you use clustering you will
automatically find where do i have to go
to find the data so this one is done
automatically by
you if you are using the proper client
or if you are using radius enterprise or
radius cloud it's transparent
because you are connected to one single
what we call the proxy that will do the
work of distribution
what you have to be careful you know we
a little bit earlier in the discussion
you ask about transactions and i told
you that it's possible to begin
something do
step one step two step three this step
one step two step three straight five
has to be done on the same instance on
the same chart
you don't want to go back into the very
complex use case where you start
something
on this node you have to finish on the
other node so kind of
to face commit global transaction
stories that you don't want that this is
a very complex
you will have a big impact so the
question will be
yes but you are telling me that redis is
distributing the data all over the place
how i manage that so you can
and this is something what we um when we
talk to
to the developers and we are kind of
doing
educations or discussion about scale
scalability we say
from day one if you know that you have a
big data set or big number of operations
per second
think about the clustering you don't
necessarily have to implement it
immediately
but understand the impact because of
what i just said
suppose you are building a system when
you have
customer and some information about the
customer like invoice or product
and they want to be linked together in
two different two or three different
keys
so what you can do with release is when
you create
when you create the key you put a hash
in
in fact by default if you put something
between two brackets in the key
this will be used to calculate the slot
so
if you want if we talk about the
customer and
inside your key you always have customer
id it could be
the customer profile it could be the
list of orders it could be the list of
calls to the crm it could be anything
you want
and in in this case
what you do is you put this hash and
redis
cluster will be sure that everything
that has the same hash or the customer
number
zero zero one everything related to
customer zero zero one will go on the
same
chart so on the same radius instance so
you will still distribute the data
but at least you can control a little
bit where the stuff is going
the idea of clustering if it's well done
it should be
transparent for the developer efficient
but giving still giving you the
flexibility of this kind of use case
in other words the application developer
has to do some sort of data modeling to
be able to place data depending on the
operations and business logic
yeah yeah if you need to have these kind
of
what we call multi-keys operation okay
yeah
that makes sense so um so what are the
trade-offs with respect to replication
if you have multiple instances do you
usually do synchronous asynchronous is
that configurable
how do you go about that it's uh it's
done
asynchronously for efficiency so
keeping in mind that what we want is we
want to be sure that default operations
are fast fast fast fast so the challenge
in this case
is since it's done asynchronously you
don't know
if the replication happened by default
so your guess will be
i will save my data on disk i will
replicate
so like that in 99.999
situations my data are safe so even if i
break something it will either take the
replica or take it from disk
i am i am safer so for most of the time
you just don't care about replication
you just activate it you say i want an
application
enabled and you will replicate the data
on some operations and this is at the
operation level this is what is
interesting when
we talk about release on many other
nosql database will have the same some
time of approach instead of giving the
rules the basic rule
is by default i want to be simple i want
to be it fast i want to be replicated
on high availability but some operations
in redis you may want to say
this specific keys when i do this
specific operations i want to be sure
that it has been replicated so i will
wait until it's done
so we have a specific command inside
redis that is called weight
in this case he will wait for the
replication to happen get an exception
if it failed
that doesn't mean the white has fail it
could be just a replication last fail
and you can choose oh i don't care i
will
eventually do it or you can retry
so by default asynchronous transparent
i don't care as a developer but if for
specific operation i can control it
and wait for the replication to happen
but in this case as you can
guess the price to pay is you have to
wait so the latency
for the overall operation will be based
on your replication factor
right and is that the same approach for
durability
when you say you can backup your redis
data to disk is it the same sort of
guarantee that you can or or
configuration that you can have so it
it's uh
i will say no the weight it really
depends of the
version of freddy's enterprise open
source or not on because
in in release enterprise the replication
is done in memory
so you control only the in-memory part
and you don't care about the disk
in open source but i think this is where
i
i will have to check in detail in which
version but i think in a new already six
version
even in open source before it was done
by disk so if you don't if the
replication is done
it was uh it was uh always
on disk so just to be sure i clarified
this
you cannot control uh to wait for a
white
replication is you control the
replication
but in some open source version the
replication is made from disk not from
memory
okay so what are the operational
complexities of
going to a clustered system versus a
single
instance and are there modules or what's
in the ecosystem to sort of
manage operational complexities what are
the operational complexities and what
how can you
manage it so it it really depends
your operational complexity in higher
availability so replication
and cluster distribution of the data
really depends of the type of
environment you have one of the things
that i want to start by
is more and more user africans use
manage services
so in this case operational is just
put yourself on the cloud you have it
you choose your plan and it's done for
you
if you are running that in-house this is
where it's becoming important to
understand how much time you want to pa
to do on ops versus doing on
buying an autopi software because
each instance of release is very simple
to do to be honest
if you if you want to start a cluster on
your laptop on two or three machines
it's not that complex you know it's you
have to
put some files start just be a little
bit careful about in which order
you do that check the configurations
then
one day you may have to do an upgrade so
you have to be careful about this so
it's just
a lot of control of the configurations
if you run with the solutions like
running on kubernetes or running on
release software
redis enterprise software this all this
part of clustering high availability
upgrade is managed for you it's one
click of a button
or a cli so it's not
complex even in open source the
important part of the open source will
give you
as much high availability as you want
but you will have to do the
configuration yourself
and it's mostly because configurations
on how you start the processes on your
different machines so
it's a very important part if you want
to do something serious
and you want to manage that yourself so
you don't want to use a manageable on
the cloud or you don't want to use an
enterprise software
you have to have a devops team or an
upstream that can
automate things because
you will add more and more if you know
exactly the size and you only need three
nodes
on three process it's not a big deal in
this case even me that i'm not a devops
expert i will be able to do it
but if the goal is to scale out and you
may add more and more data
more and more use case more and more
database you really have to be sure that
if you don't use a managed service
you have a good automation of your
configuration
yeah that makes sense so i want to drill
down into
some of the pub sub system or pub sub
support that redis has
can you talk about who the publishers
and subscribers here are can you have
like
users who are subscribing to changes
from a redis instance is that
is that how it works or is it redis to
redis so so
you have two things when we talk about
when we talk about
on your specific question pops up the
radius users when they think about pub
sub is really thinking about two
commands
publish publish subscribe and this is
command in the core release
in this case is you the key
when you know when you do a key in
release you have a key and a value
in a public publish subscribe model
the key is called a channel because it's
not persisted
so you do a publish of a publish
user user notification and you send a
message
and it's published inside race okay
nothing happen
until somebody you have a chat some
subscribers that can subscribe
to one or other messages one other
channel one or multiple channel
in this case it could be a java
application
publishing a message on many different
system
it could be one python one go
25 java and so on they will if they are
up and running when the message is sent
it will be pushed
and consumed by all the client or the
subscriber
so it's from a release application
release client application to another
release client application
so this is and when you use privilege
subscribe
this could be done either by you
your application publishing an event or
you can what we call the key space
notification inside release
you can configure release to say when
this key pattern i want to be notified
on this channel
when this pattern is a new key or it's
deleted or it
expire so for example when we were
talking about the caching exploration
earlier i can for example i didn't think
about it when you ask the questions but
i can say
if we talk about this web service
calling the
weather api i can using publish
subscribe
so publish will be done by the database
automatically every time one of the
key concerning weather api expired you
will send
an event my application will subscribe
to it
call back the service so one way of
doing
publish subscribe messaging is using the
publish subscribe
but it's a fire and forget what i fire i
don't know what's happening i don't know
if somebody is consuming it and i should
not care
so it's good for really real time
notifications and this kind of thing
if you really want to know about having
messaging where you want to
send a message persist it control the
consumer can
control only once at least once
have a pattern about retry if it fails
and so on
this is where you use redis streams as a
data structure because it's persisted
and you have the concept of consumer
that can register to a specific set of
messages
so you see you have multiple
possibilities you can even using lists
for that but
i will stay on publish subscribe on
streams but there are between uh
applications redis client application
right it's not used for replication
between radius and so on this part is
for
you building your application sure so so
you can have like a many-to-many
system or many clients publishing to a
key space and then
many clients consuming events from that
yeah okay
that's nice redis has a rich ecosystem
uh what are some
other interesting modules or extensions
that you want to mention
to our users so so the modules that i
talk are really
part of the ecosystem as you want to use
new commands on new new data structure
but you also as you mentioned a big
ecosystem of things like for example
integrating with uh tools for monitoring
connector for for grafana so you can
have a graph on a data source that will
you can use graphene in two ways to
monitor your release but also to inspect
the data you can query you can do graph
and you can inspect and
so ecosystem about monitoring in radius
is huge so you can integrate radius to
your monitoring system into graphena
into datadog and i will say also it's a
big ecosystem of having
hedis as a managed services everywhere
so redis labs is one of them
providing radius with all the modules
online but it's very important to have
something on the cloud today more and
more applications
are building this so the managed
services as a database it's key
and i will say that the
the big ecosystem is the fact that
almost
every language as a client you can use
radius with almost any language you want
so it's plugged in many many tools so
to wrap things up you know obviously
reddish still has that
simplicity grounded in its evolution so
far
where do you think redis is going in the
next couple of years what can we expect
so the the idea is to
because of the need of fast and variable
real-time applications very fast
application
redis is used more and more as a
database as a main database for your
application so this is where it's going
to
and for this you need multi-model and
multi-programming model
with the modules and a good example is
we launched
as a community in may last year already
say aye
and it's going uh mesiscio already say
and this is really where it's coming
from it's really about adding more
commands to give you more more features
to build a richer application where only
radius is needed
not seen only as a cache but working
as a database more and more okay that
that sounds really exciting
with that i'd like to wrap up doc thank
you so much for coming on this show
you're welcome this is akshay manchali
for software engineering radio thank you
for listening
become an autonomous digital enterprise
and your business can achieve
a game status intelligent predictive
systems
effortless automation and technology and
people working in harmony
this is the autonomous digital
enterprise
visit bmc.com a game for more
information
thanks for listening to sc radio an
educational program brought to you by
ieee software magazine
for more about the podcast including
other episodes visit our website at
se radio.net to provide feedback you can
comment on each episode on the website
or reach us on linkedin
facebook twitter or through our slack
channel at scradio.slack.com
you can also email us at team
sc-radio.net
this and all other episodes of sc radio
is licensed under creative commons
license 2.5
thanks for listening